A Guide to the William D. Stuart Papers, 1850-1863
Virginia Military Institute Archives
Archives, Preston Library, Virginia Military Institute
William D. Stuart Papers 1850-1863
Archives, Preston Library, Virginia Military Institute
MS 0108
The collection consists of approximately 60 items filed in 8 folders/1 box.
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The William D. Stuart Papers were donated to VMI in 1961 by Mary Venable Stuart (Mrs. William Dabney Stuart III). Mrs. Stuart's husband was the grandson of the Col. William D. Stuart.
Alternative Form
The bulk of the Stuart Papers are available in full-text format on the VMI Archives website at: http://www.vmi.edu/archives.aspx?id=10447
Provenance
The William D. Stuart papers were originally in the possession of Stuart's widow, and were passed down through the family before being donated to VMI.
Biographical/Historical Information
William Dabney Stuart was born September 30, 1830 at Staunton, Virginia, the son of Thomas Jefferson Stuart and Martha M. Dabney. He did preparatory work at the Staunton Academy and then entered the Virginia Military Institute as a cadet in July 1847. Stuart graduated from VMI in July 1850, standing 3rd in a class of 17. Following graduation he taught at VMI (1850-1853) and was subsequently principal of classical schools in Washington D.C. and Richmond, Virginia. He married Frances Harris of Loudon Co., VA; the couple had three children--Martha, Mary Bell, and William. During the Civil War Stuart briefly commanded the 15th Virginia Infantry Regiment, and was then appointed Colonel, 56th Virginia Infantry Regiment, Confederate States Army. He was mortally wounded at Gettysburg during Pickett's Charge, and died in a hospital in Staunton, VA on July 29, 1863.
Scope and Content Information
The bulk of the collection consists of the Civil War papers (ca. 60 items), 1861-1863, of Colonel William Dabney Stuart. The papers contain correspondence to and from various Confederate Army officers; morning and guard reports; military orders; and invoices and receipts documenting his brief service with the 15th Virginia Infantry Regiment and his command of the 56th Virginia Infantry Regiment. Miscellaneous other items include letters of recommendation for a United States Army Commission, 1850; a letter from Gabriel Jordan, Jr. (VMI Class of 1850) to Stuart, dated November 1854; and misc. printed materials.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged by document type and chronologically thereunder.
Contents List
- Correspondence and Military Orders
  - Letter, 1850 December 3 (Box-folder 1:1)
    From VMI Superintendent Francis H. Smith, endorsing Stuart's application for a commission in the U.S. Army
  - Letter, 1850 December 10 (Box-folder 1:1)
    From Thomas H. Williamson, VMI Professor of Engineering, endorsing Stuart's application for a commission in the U.S. Army.
  - Letter, 1850 December 10 (Box-folder 1:1)
    From VMI Professor John T. L. Preston, endorsing Stuart's application for a commission in the U.S. Army
  - Letter, 1854 November 22 (Box-folder 1:1)
    From Stuart's VMI classmate, Gabriel Jordan, Jr. A personal letter commenting on their respective marriages, jobs, future prospects.
  - Letter, 1854 November 22 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Letter, 1861 April 15 (Box-folder 1:2)
    To Virginia Governor John Letcher asking for an appointment in the Army in the event of secession.
  - Military order, 1861 May 20 (Box-folder 1:2)
    Special Orders No. 81, from HQ, Virginia Forces, Richmond. Stuart is assigned to duty with troops at the camp of instruction.
  - Letter, 1861 May 21 (Box-folder 1:2)
    From three individuals (David or Daniel Walker, Samuel Bailey, James E. Burress) to Stuart, expressing regret at Stuart's resignation as commanding officer of the Richmond City Guard.
  - Letter, 1861 May 23 (Box-folder 1:2)
    Unofficial, from Col. William Gilham to unidentified Col., regarding placement of Stuart and other officers. Written from the Camp of Instruction, Richmond.
  - Letter, 1861 July 5 (Box-folder 1:2)
    From Q.M. Dept., Richmond (Capt. Maury Garland) to Stuart, regarding materials to make a tent.
  - Letter, 1861 July 25 (Box-folder 1:2)
    From Maj. G. B. Cosby, HQ Williamsburg, to Col. Stuart (Commanding 15th Va. Regt. at King's Mill), ordering Stuart to work on fortifications at King's Mill.
  - Military order, 1861 August 13 (Box-folder 1:2)
    Special Orders No. 222. From HQ, Youngs Farm, regarding payment of troops and powers of attorney. By command of Genl. Magruder, signed by G. B. Cosby, A.A.A.G.
  - Military order, 1861 September 17 (Box-folder 1:2)
    Special Orders No. 280. From Adjutant Inspector General's office, Richmond. Stuart is promoted and assigned to the command of the 56th Virginia Regiment.
  - Letter, 1861 November 15 (Box-folder 1:2)
    Stuart to Col. George W. Munford; is honored to receive flag for his regiment.
  - Military order, 1861 November 21 (Box-folder 1:2)
    Special orders No. 232, from Adjt. Genl's office, Richmond, VA, by command of Secretary of War per John Withers. The 56th Virginia Infantry regiment ordered to Jeffersonville, VA to report to Brig. Genl. Marshall.
  - Military order, 1861 December 1 (Box-folder 1:2)
    From BG Humphrey Marshall, HQ Brigade, Pound Gap, VA. Stuart ordered to move his regiment forward by Pound Gap towards Prestonsburg, Kentucky.
  - Telegram, 1861 December 2 (Box-folder 1:2)
    From QM Dept. at Wytheville (W. Gibboney), regarding wagons.
  - Letter, 1861 December 2 (Box-folder 1:2)
    From CSA Transportation Office at Wytheville, VA (Capt. A. Meade Smith), transportation vouchers
  - Military Order, 1861 December 5 (Box-folder 1:2)
    From HQ Knoxville, TN; Stuart's regiment ordered to Nashville.
  - Telegram, 1861 December 10 (Box-folder 1:2)
    From Knoxville; Genl A. S. Johnson orders Stuart's regiment to remain with Gen. Marshall.
  - Telegram, 1861 December 11 (Box-folder 1:2)
    From Richmond, VA. Stuart's regiment to proceed to Pound Gap to report to Gen. Marshall.
  - Military Order, 1861 December 21 (Box-folder 1:2)
    Special Order No. 8. From HQ 1st Brigade, Army of Eastern KY, Camp near Paintville, by order of Gen. Marshall. Stuart's regiment to move immediately without further delay.
  - Dispatch, 1861 December 22 (Box-folder 1:2)
    From Brig. Gen. Humphrey Marshall, written at Paintville, KY. Stuart must move his regiment without delay; Marshall facing a superior force and needs reinforcements at once.
  - Military Order, 1861 December 24 (Box-folder 1:2)
    From Adjutant and Inspector General's Office, Richmond, VA. Stuart directed by Secretary of War to report to Gen. Marshall.
  - Letter, 1861 December 27 (Box-folder 1:2)
    From Lt. Col. Philip P. Slaughter, concerning orders to go to Pound Gap. " ...it is a source of the greatest mortification to me to find that...we are totally impotent..."
  - Letter, 1861 December 27 (Box-folder 1:2)
    From Lt. Col. Philip P. Slaughter to Brig. Gen. Marshall, regarding contradictory orders, illness of Stuart and men. Written from Abingdon, VA.
  - Letter, 1861 December 27 (Box-folder 1:2)
    From Regimental Surgeon Marion Howard to Stuart (who is recovering from illness), written at Abingdon, VA. Reporting on sickness in regiment, men in hospital.
  - Military Order, 1862 January 2 (Box-folder 1:3)
    Special Order No. 1, from Adjt. and Inspector Genl's office, Richmond. Col. Stuart's regiment detached from Gen. Marshall's command and will proceed to Bowling Green, Kentucky to Gen. A. S. Johnston.
  - Letter, 1862 January 4 (Box-folder 1:3)
    Lt. Col. Philip P. Slaughter to Stuart (recovering from illness); with enclosed order dated Jan 2. Regarding order to proceed to Bowling Green; praise servant Jacob; Stuart's personal belongings.
  - Letter, 1862 February 5 (Box-folder 1:3)
    To Genl. Cooper from Stuart, regarding confusion in orders to 56th Virginia and refuting statements that he had refused transportation for his command.
  - Letter, 1862 March 4 (Box-folder 1:3)
    Certificate of disability for Private William T. Cross, Company E.
  - Letter, 1862 March 8 (Box-folder 1:3)
    From Capt. Briscoe G. Baldwin to Col. Mackall, A.A.G. re: Stuart rejoining his regiment after severe illness.
  - Military Order, 1862 March 17 (Box-folder 1:3)
    General Order No. 246, from HQ, Floyd's Division, Chattanooga. Reenlisted men entitled to a 60 day furlough, but this may be suspended in case of "collision with the enemy."
  - Military Order, 1862 March 17 (Box-folder 1:3)
    General Order No. 27 (extract), from HQ, Floyd's Division, Camp Bettie Childress. Regarding movement of the command via rail.
  - Military Order, 1862 March 19 (Box-folder 1:3)
    Special Order, From HQ, Floyd's Division, Knoxville. Gen. Floyd relieved of command; regimental commanders to report to Col. George Maney.
  - Dispatch, 1862 March 19 (Box-folder 1:3)
    From Col. George Maney; Stuart to hold regiment ready to move and report on the strength of his command.
  - Military Order, 1862 March 20 (Box-folder 1:3)
    Stuart directed by Col. Maney to "take command of all the forces here, formerly of Genl Floyd's command, in the movement towards Jacksboro."
  - Military Order, 1862 March 20 (Box-folder 1:3)
    Special order, HQ Knoxville. Stuart to move tomorrow on the road to Clinton.
  - Military Order, 1862 March 20 (Box-folder 1:3)
    Special order, HQ Knoxville. Stuart to hold command (36th, 50th, 51st and 56th Virginia Regiments) in readiness to move towards Jacksboro.
  - Military Order, 1862 March 21 (Box-folder 1:3)
    Stuart not to move his command until further orders.
  - Military Order, 1862 March 21 (Box-folder 1:3)
    From Col. George Maney. Order to march towards Clinton is revoked.
  - Letter, 1862 March 31 (Box-folder 1:3)
    From Maj. General Marshall, at Lebanon. "...Your vindicating note has been successful, I imagine, in proving that you did not delay marching last winter intentionally, but the failure to join me was a great misfortune to this command. I am ready however to look forward and not backward..."
  - Letter, 1862 April 1 (Box-folder 1:3)
    John B. Floyd to Stuart, regarding releasing sick soldier (Hanshew, 50th Virginia Regt) to go home with his father.
  - Letter, 1862 April 8 (Box-folder 1:3)
    W. R. Abbot to Stuart, requesting recommendation to enter army and relaying family news.
  - Letter, 1862 April 20 (Box-folder 1:3)
    From John B. Floyd, regarding discharge of underage soldier.
  - Letter, 1862 April 30 (Box-folder 1:3)
    From Alfred L. Rives, Acting Chief, Engineering Bureau, Richmond, to Secretary of War George W. Randolph, commending Stuart, with endorsement by Randolph specifically commending his gallantry at Battle of Bethel.
  - Letter, 1862 October 26 (Box-folder 1:3)
    From R. B. Garnett, at Winchester, acknowledging receipt of report of battle of South Mountain and expressing personal regard.
  - Letter, 1862 October 30 (Box-folder 1:3)
    From Thomas D. Jeffress, Provost Marshall's Office, Lynchburg, protesting his possible return to the Regiment.
  - Letter, 1862 October 30 (Box-folder 1:3)
    From George C. Cabell, 18th Virginia Regiment, regarding a report in which he erroneously commended Capt. Jeffress.
  - Letter, 1863 March 7 (Box-folder 1:4)
    To Gen. Cooper from Lt. F. W. Nelson, Commanding Company A, 56th Virginia, requesting 25 conscripts to fill reduced ranks.
  - Letter, 1863 March 7 (Box-folder 1:4)
    From S. D. Cronin, 1st Lieut. Company I, 56th Virginia Regt., in camp near Petersburg, requesting to be absent from duty to see to business at home.
  - Letter, 1863 March 8 (Box-folder 1:4)
    From F. W. Nelson, Lieut. Company A, 56th Virginia Regt., requesting leave of absence to visit his home in Mecklenburg Co.
  - Letter, 1863 July 27 (Box-folder 1:4)
    From Nathaniel A. Flournoy, Co. K, 56th Va., to Stuart, written after the Battle of Gettysburg. Comments on casualties in regiment, wishes Stuart well, hopes he will succeed Gen. Garnett.
  - Telegram, April 10, no year (Box-folder 1:4)
    From R. L. Owens, Richmond, regarding search of trains for stolen coffee.
- Morning Reports, Rosters, Guard Reports
  - Morning Report, 56th Virginia Regiment, Camp Robertson. 1861 December 26 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Morning Report, 56th Virginia Regiment, Camp Robertson. 1861 December 27 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Special duty roster, 56th Virginia Regiment. 1862 October 22 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Guard report, 56th Virginia Regiment. no year, January 23 (Box-folder 1:5)
- Receipts and Invoices
  - Receipt for wall tent pins and poles 1861 October 14 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Receipt for ordnance (cartridges) 1861 November 25 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Ordnance shipment transmittal document 1861 November 25 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Invoice, commutation of quarters and fuel 1862 January 31 (Box-folder 1:6)
    For 1st. Lieut. George W. May, Company C. 56th VA, for period Dec. 8-31, 1861
  - Invoice, commutation of quarters and fuel 1862 January 31 (Box-folder 1:6)
    For 1st. Lieut. George W. May, Company C. 56th VA for period Jan 1-31, 1862.
  - Receipt for wall tents 1862 February 10 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Receipts (2) for muskets, cartridge boxes, etc. 1862 May 7 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Receipt for issue of clothing 1862 November 12 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Receipt commissary stores 1862 November 14 (Box-folder 1:6)
- Civil War documents-miscellaneous 1861-1863 (Box-folder 1:7)
  Includes draft of speech given upon presentation of flag to 56th Virginia, court-martial specifications and misc. other documents (7 items total).
- Confederate Veterans and Misc. Printed Material 1892-1897 (Box-folder 1:8)
  Program etc. from Roanoke area camps.